<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" lang="en">
	<channel>
		<title>University of Stirling News</title>
		<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/</link>
		<description>News from the University of Stirling</description>
		<generator>T4</generator>
		<language>en-gb</language>
		<atom:link href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />  
					<item>
				<title>New research explains dramatic reduction of ivory trade in Japan</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/new-research-explains-dramatic-reduction-of-ivory-trade-in-japan/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 11:11:00 GMT</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/new-research-explains-dramatic-reduction-of-ivory-trade-in-japan/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>With implications for global wildlife trade, research from the University of Stirling and National Institute for Environmental Studies (NIES), Japan has shown how Japan, once the largest consumer country of ivory, stopped being a destination for the product.</strong></p>
<p>Whilst a global trade ban signed in 1980 was extremely important, an interplay of cultural and economic factors also had a large impact, the researchers found.</p>
<p>Poaching for ivory has led to African and Indian elephants becoming endangered, with fewer than 500,000 left in the world, according to WWF. The biggest destination markets in the world are now China and nearby Thailand, Cambodia and Vietnam.</p>
<p>Dr Laura Thomas-Walters, from Stirling’s department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, who led the research, said: “Our research identified market drivers that led to a reduction in demand for ivory, despite the high cultural value it has had in Japan for more than 1000 years. Understand what can cause a decline in wildlife trades is vital, as many continue to cause devastating biodiversity losses worldwide.”</p>
<p>Dr Thomas-Walters worked with NIES in Japan, as well as the universities of Kent and Oxford, to analyse data from the last 40 years, since Japan signed the Convention on International&nbsp;Trade&nbsp;in Endangered Species (CITES) global trade ban in 1980.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/november/Laura-Thomas-Walters_600x700.jpg" width="700" height="600" alt="Dr Laura Thomas-Walters, from Stirling’s department of Biological and Environmental Sciences" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Dr Laura Thomas-Walters, from Stirling’s department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, led the research.</p>
<p>Dr Thomas- Walters said: “Although the CITES ban was extremely important, other elements came together in Japan, particularly during the 1990s. There was an economic recession, which fuelled a cultural shift away from the conspicuous consumption of expensive goods like ivory artefacts, jewellery or furniture.</p>
<p>“We also found that demand for ivory in Japan was passive, which means that, if it was on sale, people would buy it, but if it wasn’t they wouldn’t seek it out, unlike in countries like China, where there is a thriving black market.</p>
<p>“We found that that anti-ivory campaigns by NGOs following the CITES ban, although they may not have influenced consumers directly, put indirect pressure on retailers, which further reduced the presence of ivory in shops.”</p>
<h2>Trust in government "important"</h2>
<p>The researchers used a combination of data analysis, stakeholder interviews and literature review to test different hypotheses for the reduction in ivory imports, finding, for example, that high profile spokespeople had not been particularly effective, whilst trust in government was important.</p>
<p>Dr Thomas-Walters said: “We found that respect for the legitimacy of government authority in Japan increased the effectiveness of the trade ban. Where governments are seen to have legitimate authority, people tend to obey, whereas in other countries where respect is lower, black markets flourish.”</p>
<p>Dr Takahiro Kuba, from NIES, said: “This research, carried out with diverse stakeholders, confirmed the decline in demand for ivory for luxury items – hanko stamps for signing correspondence, for example. In addition, sluggish economic growth will accelerate the decline of the domestic market. Policymakers thus need to take account of this diminishing domestic demand when collaborating globally over sustainable management of ivory.”</p>
<p>There remains a domestic market for ivory in Japan, but the researchers concluded that this was no longer important in terms of global trade, because it involves exchanging historic rather than current imports. “Of course, it remains important to ensure that border security stays tight,” Dr Thomas-Walters added.</p>
<p>The paper <a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fconservationandsociety.org.in%2Fpreprintarticle.asp%3Fid%3D360609&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccommunications%40stir.ac.uk%7Cb9a21d9117ff4f3cb75a08dac2397e92%7C4e8d09f7cc794ccb9149a4238dd17422%7C0%7C0%7C638035849454719830%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=L2bVb0dN9JGaAjyWkQLKTudJOtVq%2Fqw7aog2NrvouJE%3D&amp;reserved=0">‘Understanding the market drivers behind the reduced demand for ivory products in Japan’</a> is published in the journal Conservation and Society.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Video games project aims to awake &#8216;sleeping giant&#8217; industry in Scotland </title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/video-games-project-aims-to-awake-sleeping-giant-games-industry-in-scotland-/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 15:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/video-games-project-aims-to-awake-sleeping-giant-games-industry-in-scotland-/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>University of Stirling experts are setting out key recommendations to boost Scotland’s video game industry.</strong></p>
<p>Academics, including Dr Michaela Hruskova from the Stirling Management School, analysed the sector through an ecosystem framework, to help the sector address key challenges and create more successful, global companies.</p>
<p>Although Scotland’s video game industry is recognised worldwide for its success, there is concern that several challenges are holding it back. Entrepreneurship and commercialisation are lacking, and smaller businesses that make up most of the industry can find growth difficult.&nbsp;There is also a lack of collective representation and strategic focus at a local or national level.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The findings are being highlighted to industry and policymakers during&nbsp;<a href="https://gamesweek.scot/">Scottish Games Week</a>, 24-28 October at a Scottish Parliament event and industry conference.&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/Michaela-Hruskova.jpg" width="700" height="600" alt="Dr Michaela Hruskova has long red hair with a fringe, black rimmed glasses and is pictured against a patterned background" loading="lazy" />
 &nbsp;</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Dr Michaela Hruskova, Lecturer in Entrepreneurship at Stirling Management School</p>
<p>Dr Helen Mullen, Lecturer in Entrepreneurship&nbsp;at the University of Glasgow Adam Smith Business School, and Principal Investigator in the project, said: “Scotland’s games sector was pioneered by entrepreneurs and has achieved notable success. However, several challenges are now holding it back, particularly the growth and sustainability of the smaller companies who make up most of the sector.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“Working with the Scottish Games Network, InGAME, and several international games experts, we have identified key challenges and actions.</p>
<p>“The sector is something of a sleeping giant with substantial potential in a growing, global market. We hope that our work will help rouse the sector, improve company successes, and increase overall entrepreneurial activity.”&nbsp;</p>
<p>Dr Michaela Hruskova, Lecturer in Entrepreneurship at University of Stirling Management School, and Co-Investigator in the project, said: “The games sector sits at the intersection of the creative and digital industries which presents it with a set of unique challenges and opportunities. Our project is seeking to explore the factors stifling growth in the sector and identify actions that can be taken to help it realise its full potential.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“We hope our work will help increase the profile of the gaming industry as one of Scotland's key sectors – and ultimately help incubate more successful companies, whose games can be enjoyed by players across the world.”&nbsp;</p>
<p>The work is a cross disciplinary project with the University of Glasgow Adam Smith Business School, University of Glasgow School of Computing Science and University of Stirling, working with industry partner the Scottish Games Network and InGAME.&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Heatwaves to impact almost every child on earth by 2050: UNICEF report</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/heatwaves-to-impact-almost-every-child-on-earth-by-2050/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 12:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/heatwaves-to-impact-almost-every-child-on-earth-by-2050/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>New research from <a href="https://www.unicef.org/">UNICEF</a>, supported by experts at the University of Stirling, has estimated that by 2050, every child in the world is expected to be exposed to worsening heatwaves.</strong></p>
<p>New report ‘<a href="https://www.unicef.org/reports/coldest-year-rest-of-their-lives-children-heatwaves">The Coldest Year Of The Rest Of Their Lives: Protecting Children From The Escalating Impacts Of Heatwaves</a>’ found at least half a billion children are already exposed to a high number of heatwaves, and by 2050 all 2.02 billion of children on earth will be exposed to high heatwave frequency.</p>
<p>The new research reveals that, even at lower levels of global heating, in just three decades, more regular heatwaves are unavoidable for children everywhere.</p>
<p>Produced in collaboration with The Data for Children Collaborative – a project involving University of Stirling Professor of Social Work, <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/991250">Lena Dominelli </a>and academics at the Universities of Edinburgh and Southampton – the report was launched in partnership with UNICEF Goodwill Ambassador Vanessa Nakate and Africa-based Rise Up Movement.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/DataforChildren_Logo3x.png" width="1772" height="426" alt="The Data for Children Collaborative logo" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>“The mercury is rising and so are the impacts on children,” UNICEF Executive Director Catherine Russell said. “Already, 1 in 3 children live in countries that face extreme high temperatures and almost 1 in 4 children are exposed to high heatwave frequency, and it is only going to get worse. More children will be impacted by longer, hotter and more frequent heatwaves over the next thirty years, threatening their health and wellbeing.</p>
<p>"How devastating these changes will be depends on the actions we take now. At a minimum, governments must urgently limit global heating to 1.5 degrees Celsius and double adaptation funding by 2025. This is the only way to save children’s lives and futures – and the future of the planet.”</p>
<p>Heatwaves are especially damaging to children, as they are less able to regulate their body temperature compared to adults. The more heatwaves children are exposed to, the greater the chance of health problems including chronic respiratory conditions, asthma, and<br>cardiovascular diseases. Babies and young children are at the greatest risk of heat-related mortality. Heatwaves can also affect children’s environments, their safety, nutrition and access to water, and their education and future livelihood.</p>
<p>The report found high heatwave duration currently impacts 538 million, or 23 per cent of, children globally. This will rise to 1.6 billion children in 2050 at 1.7 degrees warming and 1.9 billion children at 2.4 degrees warming, emphasising the importance of urgent and dramatic emissions mitigation and adaptation measures to contain global heating and protect lives.</p>
<p>Millions more children will be exposed to high heatwave severity and extreme high temperatures depending on the degree of global heating reached. Children in northern regions, especially Europe, will face the most dramatic increases in high severity heatwaves and, by 2050, nearly half of all children in Africa and Asia will face sustained exposure to extreme high temperatures.</p>
<p>“The climate shocks of 2022 provided a strong wakeup call about the increasing danger hurtling towards us,” said Vanessa Nakate, climate activist and UNICEF Goodwill Ambassador. “Heatwaves are a clear example. As hot as this year has been in almost every corner of the world, it will likely be the coldest year of the rest of our lives. The dial s being turned up on our planet and yet our world leaders haven’t begun to sweat. The only option is for us to continue to turn up the heat - on them - to correct the course we are on. World leaders must do this at COP27 for children everywhere, but especially the most vulnerable children in the most affected places. Unless they take action, and soon,<br>this report makes it clear that heatwaves will become even harsher than they are already destined to be.”</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Collaborative project to educate communities on air quality</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/collaborative-project-to-educate-communities-on-air-quality/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 15:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/collaborative-project-to-educate-communities-on-air-quality/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Air quality experts from the University of Stirling have launched a new collaborative project to help communities understand how they contribute to air pollution in their local area.</strong></p>
<p>Working with the Scottish Environment Protection Agency (SEPA) and Stirling Council, the team is currently monitoring air quality in Aberfoyle, as part of phase one of the study. The project – which will run until March 2023 – will then move on to Doune and Deanston, Thornhill, Kippen and Fintry.</p>
<p>In each village, data is collected over a one-month period, using lamppost-mounted air quality monitors and low-cost sensors deployed by residents.</p>
<p>A team from the University will host a series of community engagement events in each location, aiming to empower communities to take ownership of local air quality monitoring. These events will provide information on air pollution, its potential sources, and effects. Data from the local monitoring network will be presented and residents will be able to consider actions they may wish to take to reduce their own emissions and help reduce air pollution within their neighbourhoods.</p>
<p>Local schools will be encouraged to participate in the project with educational resources, access to SEPA’s air pollution experts and the chance to monitor pollution levels themselves. Participating schools will be encouraged to think about how they may take steps to reduce emission and improve air quality, linking such actions to the wider environmental issues, including climate change.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/UoS-Amy-McCarron_600-x-700.jpg" width="700" height="600" alt="Amy McCarron leans on a bannister. She has long, dark hair and is weather a floral patterned top." loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Amy McCarron is working on the project</p>
<p>Amy McCarron, of the University of Stirling’s Faculty of Natural Sciences, said: “Air pollution is the world’s greatest single environmental health threat, leading to serious health impacts. Nine out of ten people breathe polluted air however, since it is largely invisible, they aren’t aware of it and the harm it may be having on their health.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“Public involvement in environmental issues such as air pollution is essential for long-term, sustainable and positive change. This project will help to raise public awareness of local air quality by hosting a series of community engagement events in villages across Stirlingshire.”</p>
<p>SEPA will manage the project, developing visual tools for the public to view the data. Graham Applegate, SEPA’s Principal Policy Officer for Air Quality, said: “Improving air quality is something we all have a role to play in, as well as helping to tackle environmental pollution in general. Projects like this can enable communities to learn about air pollution and air quality in their area, as well as the issues which can influence it and the actions that can be taken to make improvements.</p>
<p>“Good air quality is essential for a good quality of life, helping maintain human health and wellbeing and our climate and habitats. It also has a vital role to play in our work towards achieving net zero.”</p>
<p>The outputs of the project will also feed into work being carried out on public engagement and behaviour change under the Scottish Government’s current Cleaner Air for Scotland 2 Strategy.</p>
<p>The next community engagement event in Aberfoyle will take place on Saturday, 5 November at 10am at the Strathard Hub.</p>
<p>The events in Doune and Deanston will take place:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thursday, 10 November (7:30pm–9pm), Rural Hall, Doune</li>
<li>Saturday, 3 December (10am-1pm), Information Centre, Doune</li>
<li>Saturday, 10 December (10am-1pm), Information Centre, Doune</li>
</ul>
<p>Future events in Thornhill, Kippen and Fintry will be announced in due course.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Low-tech gadgets have biggest impact for older people, research finds</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/low-tech-gadgets-have-biggest-impact-for-older-people-research-finds/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 13:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/low-tech-gadgets-have-biggest-impact-for-older-people-research-finds/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>New research undertaken by housing and ageing experts at the University of Stirling has found that introducing low tech gadgets to retirement living schemes has a major impact on health and well-being.</strong></p>
<p>Led by Dr Vikki McCall in partnership with leading housing association&nbsp;<a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.stonewater.org%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccraig.rennie%40stir.ac.uk%7C61a0a15b7269433fe50708dab66b8a50%7C4e8d09f7cc794ccb9149a4238dd17422%7C0%7C0%7C638022870294065997%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=0E2rCR8Nkj%2FaaTsDTtobDHdTT%2B2nkhCuXUD34uwFGD0%3D&amp;reserved=0" data-auth="Verified" data-linkindex="1">Stonewater</a>, the study, funded by the&nbsp;<a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Flongleigh.org%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccraig.rennie%40stir.ac.uk%7C61a0a15b7269433fe50708dab66b8a50%7C4e8d09f7cc794ccb9149a4238dd17422%7C0%7C0%7C638022870294065997%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=k6msZt2S%2FG8JC5S6p8tkULMwcXDhpc2fGPGDioz9fYE%3D&amp;reserved=0" data-auth="Verified" data-linkindex="2">Longleigh Foundation</a>, sought to find out how technology could best support retired living residents. Researchers found gadgets such as Fitbits, hot water dispensers, jar openers and smart speakers, which enabled small changes to residents’ daily life, had a transformative effect on their wellbeing and safety.</p>
<p>Dr McCall, a senior lecturer in Social Policy and Housing at the University of Stirling, said: “The evidence highlights a strong and recurrent theme where minor improvements to the day-to-day living of older people living in supported accommodation sites, can have the biggest impact and that routine changes can have a transformative effect. This can be from making a cup of tea independently, to joining a ‘Fitbit’ walking group or receiving medication reminders on your tablet.”</p>
<p>The research included interviews with staff and residents at four Stonewater retired living accommodation schemes across England, to identify which technology might improve living and working conditions. The technology or ‘gadget’ was then introduced, with researchers recording people’s experiences.</p>
<p>Dr McCall said: “Each piece of tech introduced was based on supporting real life barriers and challenges, as well as enhancing social opportunities and connectedness.&nbsp;Providing assistance&nbsp;with simple, routine tasks was acknowledged to make a significant difference to people.”</p>
<p>One member of staff involved in the research said: “Everything that’s been provided has made somebody more independent. Some of those small, simple gadgets like the plate, the angled spoon, the jar-opener, are amazing. Something as small as that which really does challenge someone, is huge in their lives. It’s those little, small things which have a huge impact.”</p>
<p>“This re-conceptualisation of technology – to include low-tech gadgets alongside state-of-the-art digital technology,” Dr McCall added, “shows technology as more of a process and that both high and low-tech solutions can play a critical role in daily life, supporting individual well-being, social connectedness and feelings of independence.”</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Pandemic has worsened global childhood physical inactivity crisis &#8211; and Scotland is no exception</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/pandemic-has-worsened-global-childhood-physical-inactivity-crisis--and-scotland-is-no-exception/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 17:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/pandemic-has-worsened-global-childhood-physical-inactivity-crisis--and-scotland-is-no-exception/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>The COVID-19 pandemic has exacerbated shortfalls in children’s physical activity around the world, including in Scotland, according to a new study involving the University of Stirling.</strong></p>
<p>The report by the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1123/JPAH.2022-0456">Active Healthy Kids Global Alliance</a> (AHKGA) compared 57 countries from six continents to assess global levels and trends in child and adolescent physical activity. The University of Strathclyde is the Scotland lead for the study, working alongside the Universities of Stirling and Aberdeen, Robert Gordon University, and the MRC/CSO Social and Public Health Science Unit at the University of Glasgow.</p>
<p>The new study gives the world an overall ‘D’ grade – representing success with fewer than half of children. Scotland is graded ‘B’ (success with well over half of children) in community, environment and sport and physical activity, and ‘C’ (success with approximately half of children) for active transportation and government and policy in physical activity. <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/2021/november-2021-news/widening-inequalities-in-childrens-physical-activity-research-finds/">Read more about the Scotland analysis.</a></p>
<p>The report finds that, in common with many higher-income countries, children in Scotland face inequalities in low physical activity, high levels of screen time, high obesity – as early as Primary 1 – and poor diet. In addition, while policies on activity and diet are of a high quality, they have not been fully implemented and there is a lack of specific policy on screen time.</p>
<p>The report recommends that physical activity should be promoted early in life and often, while identifying many ways to incorporate purposeful and incidental daily physical activity, such as active play, and to limit screen time. To achieve this, national monitoring would require further improvement, to inform decision-making in policy and practice.</p>
<p>It also recommends that more information should be collected on children under the age of five, particularly as the early years form a sensitive period for development and forming healthy habits.</p>
<p>Dr Simone Tomaz, of the Faculty of Health Sciences and Sport at the University of Stirling, said: “This report underlines that politicians and policymakers must do more to improve physical activity in children globally. In Scotland, there is clear intention to improve physical activity opportunities and physical activity policy. However, to improve physical activity outcomes, national monitoring must be enhanced to ensure that decision-making in policy and practice is properly informed.”</p>
<p>Professor John Reilly, of Strathclyde’s School of Psychological Sciences and Health, said the study represents the largest compilation of information to date on levels of physical activity of children and adolescents, and the data show a failing grade across the world.</p>
<p>“Scotland is no exception, and things did not improve in the decade prior to COVID-19,” he added.</p>
<p>Dr Farid Bardid, a Lecturer in Strathclyde’s School of Education, said: “This is particularly concerning as these low levels of physical activity and high levels of screen time may have worsened following the COVID-19 pandemic.”</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Voucher scheme highly effective at helping stop smoking in pregnancy, study finds</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/voucher-scheme-highly-effective-at-helping-stop-smoking-in-pregnancy-study-finds/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 10:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/voucher-scheme-highly-effective-at-helping-stop-smoking-in-pregnancy-study-finds/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A high street voucher scheme is highly effective in helping women stop smoking during pregnancy, according to new research involving the University of Stirling.</strong></p>
<p>In a new UK-wide study – led by the University of Glasgow in collaboration with Stirling, the Universities of Edinburgh and York, and Queen's University Belfast – the addition of a Love2Shop voucher incentive scheme alongside regular UK Stop Smoking Services was shown to more than double the number of women who stopped smoking during pregnancy.</p>
<p>Published in the BMJ, the phase three randomised trial examined the effectiveness and the cost-effectiveness of adding an incentive of up to £400 of high street vouchers to existing prenatal care, aimed at helping women to stop smoking in pregnancy. Almost 1,000 pregnant women who were smokers were recruited to the trial, with half receiving standard Stop Smoking Services care and the other half the same prenatal care with the addition of the incentive scheme for smoking cessation.</p>
<p>Researchers found that 26.8% of pregnant women quit smoking by the end of their pregnancy from the group which included the addition of the voucher incentive, compared to 12.3% of the control group, which received only the standard Stop Smoking Services care.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/Jennifer-McKell-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Jennifer McKell, of the University of Stirling" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Jennifer McKell, of the Faculty of Health Sciences and Sport, led the Stirling aspect of the study.</p>
<p>Maternal smoking is responsible for significant ill health and death among women and their children, including 7% of childhood hospital admissions for respiratory infection, 20% of infant deaths and 30% of babies born underweight. Research has shown that women who permanently quit smoking during pregnancy will go on to have a near normal lifespan, whereas women who continue to smoke in pregnancy and beyond are likely to lose up to 10 years of life.</p>
<p>The study took place at seven different sites across the UK – in Scotland, England, and Northern Ireland – and confirmed results through nicotine saliva testing. The participants were tested for smoking status between week 34 and week 38 of pregnancy. Most of the pregnant women who quit from both groups relapsed after their baby was born.</p>
<p>Research is ongoing, led by Professor Michael Ussher with Ms Jennifer McKell, of the University of Stirling’s Institute for Social Marketing and Health, to extend support, with financial voucher incentives, for 12 months after the baby is born, to see if mothers remain non-smokers ‘permanently’ benefitting both parent and child health.</p>
<h2>Highly effective</h2>
<p>Professor David Tappin, lead author of the study from the University of Glasgow, said: “We know that smoking in pregnancy can cause significant health problems for both mother and baby. Through this study, we have shown that the offer of high street vouchers, when offered in tandem with the current UK Stop Smoking Services, is highly effective at more than doubling smoking cessation during pregnancy, with a reduction in NHS costs over the long term.</p>
<p>Jennifer McKell led the Stirling aspect of the research, working alongside Professor Pat Hoddinott, of the Nursing, Midwifery and Allied Health Professions Research Unit. The Stirling element of the study focused on collecting and analysing mixed methods quantitative and qualitative data about prenatal care and trial processes at sites to understand the implications for practice and service delivery of the trial results. This process evaluation enables the team to understand how generalisable the findings are to different Smoking Support Service configurations working with maternity care services and, ultimately, informing how the scheme could be widened out and applied in other healthcare settings.</p>
<p>Ms McKell said: “Our team looked at how Stop Smoking Services care varied across the trial sites – examining the different types and characteristics of Stop Smoking Services offered to pregnant smokers and how they integrate with prenatal maternity services.</p>
<p>“We are hopeful our work will help health professionals caring for pregnant women and healthcare managers across the UK understand how the introduction of a voucher incentive scheme alongside Stop Smoking Services in their own healthcare settings can support pregnant women to stop smoking.”</p>
<h2>Prevention</h2>
<p>The number of women who smoke in pregnancy has been declining in countries, including the UK and America, in recent years. In Scotland, between 1995 and 2019 self-reported smoking among pregnant women declined from 30.5% to 14.6% – a decline that was matched with falls in the rates of miscarriages and small births.</p>
<p>Despite progress in helping pregnant women to stop smoking, there is evidence that engagement with smoking cessation services is variable. Interventions using financial incentives, to encourage better engagement with stop smoking services, were initially piloted in the United States and led to the development of this phase three trial in the UK.</p>
<p>Professor Linda Bauld, joint principal investigator for the study from the University of Edinburgh, said: “Our study shows just how effective high street vouchers are as a quitting aid when added to stop smoking service support. This kind of intervention is about prevention, spending up front to avoid much more serious and costly health problems for the baby and the Mum if she continues to smoke.”</p>
<p>The paper, <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/379/bmj-2022-071522">‘Financial voucher incentives provided with UK Stop Smoking Services for pregnant women: a phase III Randomised Controlled Trial’</a>, is published in The BMJ.</p>
<p>The study was funded by Cancer Research UK, the Scottish Government Chief Scientist Office, HSC Public Health Agency Northern Ireland, HSC R&amp;D Division NI, Chest Heart and Stroke Northern Ireland, The Scottish Cot Death Trust and The Lullaby Trust.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>PR student&#8217;s success marks hat-trick for Stirling at major European award </title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/pr-students-success-marks-hat-trick-for-stirling-at-major-european-award-/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 12:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/pr-students-success-marks-hat-trick-for-stirling-at-major-european-award-/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p>A public relations graduate has picked up a major academic award – marking the third time a Stirling student has been recognised at the annual EUPRERA Master Thesis Awards.</p>
<p>Anne Cumming was one of four Stirling graduates to be shortlisted in the <a href="https://euprera.org/">European Public Relations Education and Research Association (EUPRERA)</a> competition. She was announced the overall winner in the ‘Theoretical Impact Award’ category at the organisation’s Annual Congress in Vienna.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/Anne-Cumming-600x700.jpg" width="600" height="640" alt="Anne Cumming photographed with her award certificate." loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Anne collected her award at the EUPRERA Annual Congress in Vienna</p>
<p>The accolade honours those who make a significant professional or practical academic contribution to the field of public relations in Europe.</p>
<p>Anne, who is now working in the University’s Careers and Employability Service, was recognised for her dissertation which looked at the relationship between activism, documentaries, and PR theory and practice.</p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Research shows music and movement hits right note with care home residents</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/research-shows-music-and-movement-hits-right-note-with-care-home-residents/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 10:10:30 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/research-shows-music-and-movement-hits-right-note-with-care-home-residents/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A pilot study by the University of Stirling has found that music and movement can have a positive impact on the health and wellbeing of care home residents – and could lead to similar activities being rolled out on a wider scale.</strong></p>
<p>The study, conducted by researchers from the Faculty of Health Sciences and Sport, in partnership with wellbeing, arts and fitness company danceSing Care, followed 47 residents from 10 Balhousie Care Group homes across Scotland over a period of 12 weeks as they evoked memories and improved their mental, emotional and physical wellbeing.</p>
<p>Residents and caregivers got their toes tapping, hands clapping and voices singing as they enjoyed digital music and movement resources created by the danceSing Care team in consultation with NHS healthcare professionals.</p>
<p>Over the study period, residents joined the online danceSing Care sessions four times per week, where they were encouraged to take part in a variety of fun and meaningful activities including everything from chair and standing fitness, music and singing, bespoke Memory Lane radio shows, and musical concerts.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/Balhousie-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="danceSing initiative at Balhousie Care Home" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Benefits: Balhousie reported that the collective mood of residents visibly improved during danceSing sessions.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The sessions proved increasingly popular as the weeks went on, and a range of benefits and improvements to residents’ wellbeing have been reported.</p>
<p>Academics looked at a number of aspects of participants’ health and wellbeing, spanning anxiety and depression, stress and loneliness, sleep satisfaction, and indications of frailty such as appetite and unintentional weight loss. The study showed improvements in a number of areas.</p>
<p>Balhousie Care Group also reported that the collective mood of the residents was visibly improved during the sessions. Even those participants who were demotivated at the beginning were visibly happier by the end of the session, or those not actively taking part still enjoyed the benefits of being present while the session took place.</p>
<p>The numerous benefits and joy from the danceSing Care sessions were exemplified in moments such as one resident, after being hospitalised, returning to the home and immediately asking to take part in a danceSing Care session. As the programme progressed, residents waited in the lounge for the sessions to start, showing enthusiasm and excitement.</p>
<p>It was noted that residents participated more in each movement session as the weeks went on, with visible improvements in physical strength. Staff members commented that the success of the programme was visible in the residents’ “eyes, smiles and more smiles”, and one resident described the mood-boosting music sessions as being “good for the soul”.</p>
<p>The study also identified challenges to delivering the programme, such as staff time and availability of suitable technology, so solutions to these can be incorporated into any future activity.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Forth Valley set to benefit from landmark new health partnership</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/forth-valley-set-to-benefit-from-landmark-new-health-partnership/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 13:10:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/october-2022-news/forth-valley-set-to-benefit-from-landmark-new-health-partnership/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>An ambitious landmark partnership between the University of Stirling, Forth Valley College and NHS Forth Valley has launched today – with the mission to improve patient care and treatments, and boost health research and staff learning across the region.</strong></p>
<p>The Forth Valley University College NHS Partnership is the first formal regional partnership between a health board, university, and college in Scotland. Building on a long-standing relationship between the three institutions, it will work across four priority areas: learning, careers, research, and innovation.</p>
<figure class="float-right u-m-1"><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/october/Forth-Valley-Health-Partnership-logo-250-349x182.jpg" width="349" height="182" alt="Forth Valley Health Partnership logo" loading="lazy" />
</figure>
<p>It aims to deliver transformational change to the health of the area through the delivery of new learning and development opportunities for students and staff working across local health and care services.</p>
<p>The collaboration will bring together the organisations’ unique wealth of knowledge, expertise, and experience to create a nerve centre for world-class research and innovation. It will also directly respond to the needs of local people by reaching into a wide range of settings – from hospitals, health centres and social care settings to care homes and classrooms.</p>
<p><strong>Cathie Cowan, Chief Executive of NHS Forth Valley, said:</strong> “We already have a strong, long-standing relationship with the University of Stirling and Forth Valley College. This exciting new Partnership will build on this work and bring together a wealth of knowledge, expertise and experience to help unlock research funding and develop new learning opportunities for our current and future workforce.</p>
<p>“It will also help us trial new tests and treatments and drive forward innovations to improve the health and wellbeing of local people across Forth Valley and beyond.”</p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>University of Stirling celebrates Singapore graduates</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/university-of-stirling-celebrates-singapore-graduates/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 11:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/university-of-stirling-celebrates-singapore-graduates/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>The University of Stirling is today celebrating the graduation of students from its programmes delivered at the Singapore Institute of Management (SIM).</strong></p>
<p>The two institutions formed an international partnership in 2011, which sees students taught in Singapore by travelling lecturers from University of Stirling Management School. Supported by staff at SIM, students can choose from a range of courses and graduate with a University of Stirling degree.</p>
<p>Today, the University of Stirling marks the achievement of almost 100 graduates in BA Retail Marketing, BA Marketing, BA Sports Studies and Marketing and BA Events Management. It is the first University of Stirling-SIM ceremony to be held in person since 2019, due to the pandemic.</p>
<p>Professor Sir Gerry McCormac, Principal and Vice-Chancellor of the University of Stirling, said: “On behalf of the University of Stirling, I send my warmest congratulations to our students graduating in Singapore today. We’re incredibly proud of the efforts of all our graduates and wish them the very best as they step into the next chapter of their lives.”</p>
<p>The University’s Deputy Principal (Internationalisation), Professor Neville Wylie, and Executive Director for Internationalisation and Partnerships, Dr Lee Zhuang, attended the ceremony.</p>]]></description>
				<category>graduation</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Stirling Golfers Scoop Silverware at Montrose </title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/stirling-golfers-scoop-silverware-at-montrose/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 13:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/stirling-golfers-scoop-silverware-at-montrose/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Stirling sport scholars Lorna McClymont and George Cannon have won the first round of the R&amp;A Student Tour Series – the Stirling International – at Montrose Golf Links.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>McClymont, last year’s BUCS Order of Merit winner, started her season in the same vein of form as she broke the course record on day one with a stunning 13-under par 60. Despite a tougher second round, the Sports Studies student held her nerve to hold off Lucy Jamieson of St Andrews by one shot.</p>
<p>The win, whilst not as comfortable as she may have hoped, still marks a great start to the season. Fittingly, it was also further cause for celebration as the result was achieved on the day of her 22<sup>nd</sup> birthday.<br> <br> Commenting on her rollercoaster victory at Montrose, the 22-year-old said: “I’ll learn from both rounds of golf. Yesterday it was good to learn to have that control and how it feels. Today it was good because I learned there are times when golf doesn’t always go your way, and you have to take it on the chin and learn from it. That’s golf.”</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/september/george-cannon-montrose-1080x631-RandA.jpg" width="1080" height="631" alt="George Cannon tees off at hole 18 of the Montrose Links golf course" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">George Cannon tees off on hole 18. Photo: R&amp;A Golf.</p>
<p>Meanwhile in the men’s event, one of Stirling Golf team’s newest recruits - 19-year-old George Cannon - fought off stiff competition from fellow teammate Will Coxon and Edge College’s Ben Willis, securing his first win on the Student Tour Series.</p>
<p>In a three-way playoff, it took three rounds of the par-4 second hole before the Business and Finance student sealed the win.</p>
<p>Have only just been called up to the team in the week building up to the tournament, Cannon was full of gratitude for the opportunity to tee it up with the UK’s best student golfers. He said: “I’ve worked really hard over the summer and Dean (Robertson – University of Stirling’s Head of Golf) has put in a lot of hard work with me. He’s given me a lot of confidence and you can’t beat that. I only got in the team last week and so it’s a great start. Happy days.”</p>
<p>Both McClymont and Cannon will now look forward to the next event in the Student Tour Series, held at Le Golf National in France, which hosted the 1028 Ryder Cup, from 24-26 October.</p>
<p>Read more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.randa.org/en/championships/student-tour-series">The R&amp;A Student Tour Series</a>&nbsp;and the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/student-life/sport-at-stirling/performance-sport/golf/">University of Stirling high performance golf programme</a>.</p>]]></description>
				<category>sports-centre</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Moving mussels: new insights into shellfish farming</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/moving-mussels-new-insights-into-shellfish-farming/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 09:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/moving-mussels-new-insights-into-shellfish-farming/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Researchers have identified how mussel larvae move – giving mussel and other shellfish farmers important insights into where and how to grow them.</strong></p>
<p>The University of Stirling’s Institute of Aquaculture used genetic testing of mussels at sample sites along Scotland’s west coast combined with mathematical modelling to understand where mussels grow well – and it’s all about the current.</p>
<p>PhD researcher Ana Corrochano-Fraile said: “Mussel growing has been a bit of a black box. The larvae float in the water, we put ropes at sea and larvae appear there. If the stock goes down, we don’t know why. If the quality goes down, we don’t know why.</p>
<p>“Our model shows us how the larvae move in the currents, from south to north. We found that, in 30 days, a cloud of larvae can move from the Scottish border near Stranraer up to Islay, for example. They then attach to substrate – anything solid in the water, which could be ropes – and grow for one and a half years until they start reproducing. The next generation of larvae is carried on the current from Islay to the Outer Hebrides in 30 days – that’s a lot further, because the current is faster there.</p>
<p>“For example, we found that 90 per cent of the mussels in Loch Roag on Lewis have come from Barra. Knowing where mussels come from and where they go tells us a lot about the best and worst locations for farms.”</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Evaluation finds extension of distress intervention during pandemic was a success</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/evaluation-finds-extension-of-distress-intervention-during-pandemic-was-a-success/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 10:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/evaluation-finds-extension-of-distress-intervention-during-pandemic-was-a-success/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p>A ground-breaking mental health programme which supports people in distress was successfully extended during the pandemic, according to a new evaluation led by the University of Stirling.</p>
<p>Health experts from&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nmahp-ru.ac.uk/">the Nursing, Midwifery and Allied Health Professions Research Unit (NMAHP-RU)</a> at Stirling and Glasgow Caledonian University conducted the evaluation into the Distress Brief Intervention (DBI), which was extended as part of Scotland’s national COVID-19 response.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.gov.scot/publications/evaluation-extended-distress-brief-intervention-programme-summary-findings/">The evaluation</a>&nbsp;found that the programme – which was first developed in 2016 to support people in distress –&nbsp;adapted and integrated successfully with the NHS24 Mental Health Hub during the pandemic to deliver connected compassionate support to more people across Scotland.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/256451">Professor Edward Duncan</a>, of the&nbsp;<a href="/about/faculties/health-sciences-sport/">Faculty of Health Sciences and Sport</a>&nbsp;and NMAHP-RU at Stirling, said: “Our evaluation found that is possible to extend ways in which DBI is delivered without impacting on the positive health outcomes we found in the wider evaluation of the core DBI programme. The evaluation findings support the ongoing implementation of this successful interagency programme to support people in distress.”</p>
<p>National DBI programme manager Kevin O’Neill, said: “I must thank the evaluation team for the report and emerging findings. The report validates all the tremendous work of the DBI community, who are inspired and committed to using the learning and recommendations, in support of the continuous improvement to provide the best connected, compassionate support possible.</p>
<p>“I pay the highest tribute to the DBI community who have demonstrated incredible commitment, innovation, flexibility, creativity, and adaptability in how they have responded to the pandemic, with all involved mobilising their collective assets, not only maintaining the provision of connected compassionate support during these challenging times but answering the call to expand its reach at significant pace and scale.</p>
<p>“Special acknowledgement goes to all our frontline colleagues, which now includes NHS24 and the third sector DBI community, who by working together, day in and day out have provided connected compassionate support to over 30,000 people in distress, 10,000 of whom have been referred by NHS24.”</p>
<p>The DBI was initially developed in 2016 to enable frontline workers in areas such as emergency departments, police, ambulance service, and primary care trained to ease a person’s distress. If appropriate, they can then be referred to the DBI level two service, with the promise of support within 24 hours.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Pioneering tool to support design of dementia friendly spaces</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/pioneering-tool-to-support-design-of-dementia-friendly-spaces/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 10:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/pioneering-tool-to-support-design-of-dementia-friendly-spaces/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Experts from the University of Stirling have created a new tool to support families, businesses and professionals to make homes, premises and public places more accessible to an ageing population and those living with dementia.</strong></p>
<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dementia.stir.ac.uk/our-services/ea-ddat">Environments for Ageing and Dementia Design Assessment Tool</a> (EADDAT) combines the latest research on designing for cognitive change with the expertise of leading architects based at the University’s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dementia.stir.ac.uk/">Dementia Services Development Centre</a> (DSDC). It replaces DSDC’s Dementia Design Audit Tool which was first developed in 2008 and has influenced the design of care buildings worldwide.</p>
<p>Following successful trials by Transport for London and Kirklees Council, EADDAT is now available to those seeking to make homes, restaurants, cafes and public buildings more accessible.</p>]]></description>
				<category>dementia, policy</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>University of Stirling pays tribute to Her Majesty The Queen</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/university-of-stirling-pays-tribute-to-her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 18:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/university-of-stirling-pays-tribute-to-her-majesty-queen-elizabeth-ii/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong><span data-contrast="auto">The University of Stirling is deeply saddened at the passing of Her Majesty The Queen.</span></strong></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">As Britain’s longest serving monarch,&nbsp;</span><span data-contrast="auto">Elizabeth II has been the figurehead of the United Kingdom and the Commonwealth for more than 70 years, and throughout her reign has enjoyed close links to the higher education sector.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:160,&quot;335559740&quot;:259}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto"><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/september/QV-002-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="HRH Queen Elizabeth opening Queens Court at the University of Stirling" loading="lazy" />
 </span></p>
<p class="c-image-caption"><span data-contrast="auto">Her Majesty The Queen, pictured with former Principal Professor Tom Cottrell, unveiled a plaque in Queen's Court during her visit to the University in 1972.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">In 1967, Her Majesty signed the University of Stirling’s Royal Charter, officially launching the institution by Royal Command and five years later, in 1972, she was welcomed on to campus as part of a Royal Visit to Stirling and formally opened Queen’s Court.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:160,&quot;335559740&quot;:259}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">In more recent times, the University has had the honour of receiving two Queen’s Anniversary Prizes in recognition of its transformational work in social marketing and health research, and for its innovation in aquaculture.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:160,&quot;335559740&quot;:259}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/september/Principal-meets-the-Queen_1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Professor Sir Gerry McCormac shakes the hand of Queen Elizabeth II at Buckingham Palace" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Professor Sir Gerry McCormac accepted the Queen's Anniversary Prize for Higher and Further Education in recognition of the University's ground-breaking social marketing research, at a ceremony at Buckingham Palace in 2014.</p>
<p>Professor Sir Gerry McCormac, Principal and Vice-Chancellor of the University of Stirling, said: “We are deeply saddened to hear of the passing of Her Majesty&nbsp;The Queen and on behalf of the University, I express my sincere condolences to the Royal Family.&nbsp;</p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">“Throughout her remarkable reign, Her Majesty has been a great friend to the higher education sector and her continued support for the work undertaken by our researchers has been <span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun" data-ccp-charstyle-defn="{&quot;ObjectId&quot;:&quot;ffb1a26e-3efd-4472-a605-f7f36f6da632|6&quot;,&quot;ClassId&quot;:1073872969,&quot;Properties&quot;:[469775450,&quot;normaltextrun&quot;,201340122,&quot;1&quot;,134233614,&quot;true&quot;,469778129,&quot;normaltextrun&quot;,335572020,&quot;1&quot;,469778324,&quot;Default Paragraph Font&quot;]}">a valuable contribution to the University’s success over its 55-year history</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">. </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="eop" data-ccp-charstyle-defn="{&quot;ObjectId&quot;:&quot;ffb1a26e-3efd-4472-a605-f7f36f6da632|7&quot;,&quot;ClassId&quot;:1073872969,&quot;Properties&quot;:[469775450,&quot;eop&quot;,201340122,&quot;1&quot;,134233614,&quot;true&quot;,469778129,&quot;eop&quot;,335572020,&quot;1&quot;,469778324,&quot;Default Paragraph Font&quot;]}"> </span></span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:160,&quot;335559740&quot;:259}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto"><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">“</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">In her passing, the UK has lost not </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">only</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">&nbsp;a head of state, but a champion for the many causes and charities to which she dedicated her time and provided such inspiration</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">. </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="eop"> </span></span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559738&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:0,&quot;335559740&quot;:240}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto"><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">“</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">Colleagues will remember </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">T</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">he Queen</span> <span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">not only </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">for her </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">sense of duty and devotion to a </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">lifetime of service to the nation</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun"> but for her compassion and the kindness she showed to everyone she met</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">.</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">”</span></span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335559738&quot;:0,&quot;335559739&quot;:0,&quot;335559740&quot;:240}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none"><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">In tribute, </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">all </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">u</span></span><span data-contrast="none"><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">niversity </span></span><span data-contrast="none"><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">flags will fly at half-mast</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun"> and</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun"> a </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">b</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">ook of </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">c</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">ondolence </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">for staff and students </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">will be made available </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">from </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">9am tomorrow </span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">in the University Chaplaincy</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="normaltextrun">. </span></span></p>
<p>An official book of condolence has been made available on <a title="Stirling Council Book of Condolence" href="https://stirling.gov.uk/book-of-condolence/">Stirling Council's website</a>.&nbsp;Further information on&nbsp;public events and official proceedings following The Queen's death, are expected to be made available shortly on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.royal.uk/">the Royal Family website</a>.</p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Tech project succeeds in connecting care home residents during pandemic</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/tech-project-succeeds-in-connecting-care-home-residents-during-pandemic/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 09:09:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/tech-project-succeeds-in-connecting-care-home-residents-during-pandemic/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A pioneering project introducing iPads to care homes during the pandemic had a significant impact on social isolation, according to experts at the University of Stirling.</strong></p>
<p>Working in collaboration with the Scottish Government’s&nbsp;<a href="https://tec.scot/">Technology Enabled Care (TEC) Programme</a> and the <a href="https://www.dhi-scotland.com/">Digital Health &amp; Care Innovation Centre (DHI)</a><a href="https://eur03.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.dhi-scotland.com%2F&amp;data=05%7C01%7Ccommunications%40stir.ac.uk%7Ce791664c57d940651e3108da90ab1ff7%7C4e8d09f7cc794ccb9149a4238dd17422%7C0%7C0%7C637981361904522069%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C3000%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=R7t8Lge0oiIyszqw4VOPXucvjKToEww9MfGSGW%2Far40%3D&amp;reserved=0">,</a> researchers led by dementia specialist Dr Grant Gibson, looked at the success of the ‘Connecting Residents in Scotland’s Care Homes’ (CRSCH) initiative, finding it played an important role in supporting residents of care homes to maintain contact with family members during Covid-19 lockdowns.</p>
<p>Launched in November 2020, CRSCH aimed to equip all care homes in Scotland with digital devices, connectivity, training and support to tackle social isolation and help residents enjoy the benefits of online access.</p>
<p>Researchers found that through the project, 75% of the 1398 registered care homes in Scotland were provided with at least one iPad, while 115 took possession of multiple devices.&nbsp; iPads were used to support regular video calls between residents and family members, with the technology also found to provide further benefits including physical activity and entertainment.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research, policy</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>One in four children referred to mental health services in Scotland have suicidal thoughts or behaviours, study suggests</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/one-in-four-children-referred-to-mental-health-services-in-scotland-have-suicidal-thoughts-or-behaviours-study-suggests/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 14:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/september-2022-news/one-in-four-children-referred-to-mental-health-services-in-scotland-have-suicidal-thoughts-or-behaviours-study-suggests/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A quarter of children referred to mental health services in Scotland have been thinking about or attempted suicide – and face a postcode lottery as to whether they will be assessed or treated, a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyt.2022.914479/full">new study</a> suggests.</strong></p>
<p>Suicide among children and young people is a leading cause of death globally and, in the UK, the number of suicides among under-25s has been continually rising since 2017. Scotland has the highest rate of suicides among children in the UK – however, the number referred to mental health services for suicidality, and the care they receive, is largely unknown.</p>
<p>Funded through a PhD from the Economic and Social Research Council, part of UK Research and Innovation, researchers at the University of Stirling have addressed this dearth of evidence by reviewing referrals to Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services (CAMHS) in two of Scotland’s NHS board areas. They found 25% of all referrals – those made to both boards across a six-month period – were for children who had been thinking about or had attempted suicide – and a third of those were under the age of 12.</p>
<p>The study also highlighted a significant disparity in the response of health boards to children referred for suicidality. In the first health board, more than two thirds (69%) were not offered a face-to-face assessment and just 8% of those assessed were offered treatment immediately. By contrast, the second health board – which had a specific suicide and self-harm team – offered face-to-face assessments to most (82%), with 66% of those offered treatment.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>First festival of biodiversity for the Forth Valley </title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/first-festival-of-biodiversity-for-the-forth-valley-/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 09:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/first-festival-of-biodiversity-for-the-forth-valley-/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>The University of Stirling, in conjunction with <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/about/scotlands-international-environment-centre/">Scotland’s International Environment Centre (SIEC)</a>, will host its first ever Festival of Biodiversity from Friday, 16 to Sunday, 18 September.</strong></p>
<p>Held on the University’s beautiful campus, and across the Forth Valley, over the course of three days, the Festival invites the public to take part in a series of events and activities including nature walks, expert Q&amp;As, interactive workshops and film screenings to explore biodiversity in action across the planet, and at home in Scotland.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/Alistair-Jump---University-of-Stirling-text-pic.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Professor Alistair Jump" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Professor Alistair Jump</p>
<p>Professor Alistair Jump, Dean of the Faculty of Natural Sciences, said: “Broadly speaking, ‘biodiversity’ refers to every living thing in the world - including plants, fungi, bacteria, animals, and humans – and the ecosystems that support life. Humans depend on healthy ecosystems to stabilise the climate, purify the air, protect our coastlines, and provide us with sufficient food, clean water and raw materials to survive.</p>
<p>“The Festival will celebrate biodiversity, across themes including mountain woodland restoration, discovering biodiversity beneath the ground, the re-beavering of Scotland's rivers and how the food we eat affects biodiversity.</p>
<p>“We want everyone to be as excited as we are about biodiversity, and to join the fight against its decline.”</p>
<p>Activities and events will delivered by local organisations across the Forth Valley on Friday and Saturday, with Sunday seeing the University’s Pathfoot Building house indoor events, talks, workshops, and stalls from a range of environmental organisations, and provide exhibition space for biodiversity-themed artwork. It will also be the meeting point for outdoor activities such as nature walks, forest bathing, tree coring and mindfulness walks.</p>
<p><strong>Entry is free, all welcome. For more information visit <a href="http://www.festivalofbiodiversity.stir.ac.uk">www.festivalofbiodiversity.stir.ac.uk</a></strong></p>
<p>SIEC is funded by a combined £22m investment from the UK and Scottish Governments, as part of the Stirling and Clackmannanshire City Region Deal, with additional funding from the University of Stirling and Clackmannanshire Council.</p>
<p><strong>Read more about&nbsp;<a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/about/scotlands-international-environment-centre/">Scotland’s International Environment Centre (SIEC)</a></strong></p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Historic children&#8217;s home archive opens with donation from former resident</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/historic-childrens-home-archive-opens-with-donation-from-former-resident/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 09:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/historic-childrens-home-archive-opens-with-donation-from-former-resident/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A <a href="https://collections.stir.ac.uk/archive-collections/archive-collections-a-z/aberlour-scotlands-childrens-charity/">new archive</a> making more than a century’s worth of records from Aberlour Children’s Charity accessible for the first time has been officially opened by a former resident.</strong></p>
<p>Ron Aitchison, who spent his childhood in the care of Aberlour Orphanage in the 1950s and 1960s, welcomed the new catalogue created by the University of Stirling, by donating a number of his own items to the collection.</p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>&#163;2m research to study impact of place and stigma on older disabled adults</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/2m-research-to-study-impact-of-place-and-stigma-on-older-disabled-adults/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 08:08:59 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/2m-research-to-study-impact-of-place-and-stigma-on-older-disabled-adults/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>New research exploring the impact of stigma on fuelling inequalities experienced by UK disabled adults in later life has secured funding of £2m.</strong></p>
<p>Led by University of Stirling housing expert Dr Vikki McCall, the study ‘Intersectional Stigma of Place-based Ageing (ISPA)’, will investigate and identify how stigma related to age, disability, and where someone lives, creates additional barriers for older people living with sensory and mobility impairments.</p>
<p>Supported by the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC) – part of UK Research and Innovation – the five-year project will result in researchers working in collaboration with disabled adults to use their findings to develop guidance on the actions and modifications required in people’s homes and environments to allow this group to age well in their communities.</p>
<p>The project will also build an ‘Inclusive Living Alliance’ – a UK wide network made up of organisations from housing, health, social care and the third sector – to road test this guidance and focus on long-term policy change. Fifteen project partners have already signed up to the Alliance, including the <a href="https://www.housinglin.org.uk/">Housing LIN</a> and <a href="https://www.sfha.co.uk/">Scottish Federation of Housing Associations</a>. &nbsp;</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Major report sets out recommendations for living well with dementia</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/major-report-sets-out-recommendations-for-living-well-with-dementia/</link>
				<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 15:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/major-report-sets-out-recommendations-for-living-well-with-dementia/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A major forum into housing and dementia, co-chaired by a University of Stirling academic, has published a series of recommendations on living well with the condition. </strong></p>
<p>Living well at home: Housing and Dementia in Scotland, is the report of the National Housing and Dementia Forum, which was established by the Scottish Government in 2021.</p>
<p>The report was launched by Dr Vikki McCall, Ashley Campbell co-chair of the Forum and Kevin Stewart MSP, Minister for Mental Wellbeing and Social Care, during a visit to Varis Court, a housing with care development in Forres managed by&nbsp;<a title="Hanover Scotland" href="https://www.hanover.scot/">Hanover Scotland</a> and featured as a case study in the report.</p>
<p>The report sets out recommendations for how the Scottish Government and partner organisations can better support people to live well with dementia. It highlights the need for tenure blind services ensuring people can access help when they need it, regardless of their housing tenure. The report also advocates the importance of initiating conversations about housing much earlier, tackling the stigma around aging and ensuring housing and health &amp; social care partners work closely to guarantee the best outcomes for people living with dementia, their families, and carers.</p>
<p>There are currently approximately 90,000 people living in Scotland with dementia, with this number expected to increase significantly as the population continues to age. Recognising the importance of supporting people with dementia to remain well at home for as long as possible, the Scottish Government established the National Housing and Dementia Forum in 2021.</p>
<p>The Forum, independently co-chaired by Ashley Campbell, policy and practice manager at Chartered Institute of Housing Scotland (CIH Scotland) and Lesley Palmer, chief architect of the&nbsp;<a title="Dementia Services Development Centre" href="https://www.dementia.stir.ac.uk/">Dementia Services Development Centre</a> (DSDC) at the University of Stirling, gathered evidence from a wide range of experts and people with lived experience of dementia.</p>
<p>The Forum considered four key themes through online evidence sessions and one to one meetings: housing options and adaptations; access to advice and information; support for people living with dementia; and moving home in later life.</p>
<p>Dr Vikki McCall attended the launch and spoke on behalf of her colleague Lesley Palmer, chief architect of the Dementia Services Development Centre (DSDC) at the University of Stirling and co-chair of the Forum. Dr. McCall commented:</p>
<p>“The University of Stirling is honoured to have been able to support the research and writing of this report. Our country’s housing provision, design, and tenure play an integral role in supporting people living with dementia, their care partners, and families to maintain their lives (physically, socially, and economically) and this was reinforced in the evidence we collected over the past year, during the research and writing of this report. To enable people with dementia to remain with their families, in their communities, and at home, we must invest in housing that supports their needs. This report recognises this and sets out relevant and realistic recommendations, for Scotland to lead on housing as a commitment within post-diagnostic support.”</p>
<p>Ashley Campbell, policy and practice manager at CIH Scotland and Forum co-chair, added:</p>
<p>“The housing sector has a key role to play in supporting people to live well with dementia, ensuring the best outcomes requires partnership working across housing and the built environment, health and social care, and the third sector. We hope this report acts as a catalyst for further conversations and partnership working on how we can all make a positive difference for people living with dementia.</p>
<p>“We look forward to working with the Scottish Government and others to ensure that the Forum’s recommendations are reflected in national policy and local services.”</p>
<p>On reviewing the report Kevin Stewart MSP, Scottish Government Minister for Mental Wellbeing and Social Care said:</p>
<p>“The Scottish Government wants more people living with dementia to be able to live well at home for as long as possible. I am very grateful to all members of the National Housing and Dementia Forum for all the work they have put into developing this report. Housing has a huge role to play in how we support people living with dementia to feel safe and able to play an active role in their local communities as their needs change.</p>
<p>“This report comes at a good time as the Scottish Government starts work to develop a new dementia strategy for Scotland. Learning from the recommendations in this report and great practice in places like Varis Court is something I am keen for the new strategy to embrace. I look forward to working together with people with lived experience of dementia and other partners to deliver a strategy that keeps Scotland at the forefront of Dementia Policy internationally”</p>
<p>Angela Currie, Chief Executive of Hanover Scotland said:</p>
<p>“Hanover are delighted to have been part of this important work and we welcome the recommendations. We have our own Dementia Strategy and are working towards being able to fully support those with dementia both now and in the future. It is clear that more needs to be done in Scotland to help those on their dementia journey. Our Varis Court development in Forres is an exemplar of an integrated approach, but we need even more of these specialist services, particularly in the social rented sector if we are to meet the needs of the expanding population of older people.”</p>
<p>The full report can be <a title="CIH Scotland" href="https://www.cih.org/media/uozlr0fj/living-well-at-home.pdf">downloaded from CIH Scotland</a>.</p>]]></description>
				<category>dementia</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Lessons for Police Scotland in introduction of body cameras</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/lessons-for-police-scotland-in-introduction-of-body-cameras/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 16:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/lessons-for-police-scotland-in-introduction-of-body-cameras/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>There is widespread public support for police officers in Scotland to wear body cameras when attending incidents, but certain pitfalls must be avoided, new research highlights.</strong></p>
<p>Police Scotland commissioned researchers from the University of Stirling to understand how body worn video (BWV) has been used effectively, elsewhere in the UK and internationally, in ways that best support policing and maintain public confidence. &nbsp;</p>
<p>The researchers emphasised that before introducing BWV, Police Scotland must ensure that processes for effective governance and scrutiny, particularly data handling, are in place.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/William-Webster--University-of-Stirling-T4-text-pic.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Prof William Webster" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Professor William Webster&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/people/256405">Professor William Webster</a>, of the <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/about/faculties/stirling-management-school/">University of Stirling Management School</a>, who led the report, said: “Body worn video seems a simple concept – it’s a camera that police carry around – but how it’s used influences a complicated set of relationships, starting with that between the citizen and the state.</p>
<p>“It’s important to understand the consequences and how the technology shapes behaviour, to make sure that it is being used in the interests of society and not just in the interests of policing.”</p>
<h2>Clear protocols needed</h2>
<p>He said the research showed a gap between protocol and practice in other forces, where protocols were too vague.</p>
<p>“It’s very important to establish clear protocols and training for how BWV should be used,” Professor Webster said. “For example, giving a warning and switching on when an incident is about to start.</p>
<p>“There also needs to be a clear plan for what happens to the recording, which is citizens’ data – is it downloaded by the officer at the end of a shift? Where to? Who can access it? What circumstances justify keeping it?</p>
<p>“And there must be an oversight mechanism, such as dip sampling, where random recordings are checked, possibly by lay people, to monitor how BWV is being used.</p>
<p>“Police Scotland commissioned this research because they want to be very careful about how they introduce emerging technologies. They have a huge opportunity in that they can learn from what other forces and countries have done well and less well.”</p>
<h2>Benefits&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Police Scotland Chief Superintendent Matt Richards said: “The Chief Constable has underlined his support for the wider introduction of body worn video cameras in Scotland and Dame Elish Angiolini recommended our plans to expand their use be accelerated in her independent review of complaints.</p>
<p>“BWV requires significant investment but has the potential to enhance the vital bond of trust and confidence policing in Scotland has with our fellow citizens and which underpins our legitimacy. BWV can also lead to swifter justice outcomes.</p>
<p>“We agree a wider roll-out of BWV must be ethical and transparent and we are encouraged that our previous national public consultation in 2021 found overwhelming support for its introduction. The feedback we received will help inform our BWV Code of Practice. We are also taking advice and guidance on ethical, human rights and civil liberties considerations.</p>
<p>“We are grateful to Professor Webster for this work which adds value to our thinking and approach.”</p>
<p>The researchers, from the Centre for Research into Information, Surveillance and Privacy (CRISP) at Stirling, carried out a literature review of existing research, including usage and scrutiny reports from other countries, and interviewed 11 senior policymakers and practitioners in the field, including the UK’s data protection, information and surveillance commissioners and Scotland’s biometrics commissioner.</p>
<h2>Elements to consider</h2>
<p>They highlighted several elements that had often not been properly considered by other forces before implementation.</p>
<p>Professor Webster said: “The police like BWV because it offers them protection during risky encounters, de-escalating violence, for example, and collects evidence for prosecutions. But it also puts the police under surveillance. For instance, elsewhere, it has picked up officers smoking on duty, or using a mobile phone when driving, so that has to be considered.</p>
<p>“Then there needs to be further thought about usage during sensitive circumstances, such as at a mosque, or when responding to domestic violence. Trust in technologies and in the police can easily be lost.”</p>
<p>Martyn Evans, Chair of the Scottish Police Authority, said: “The use of Body Worn Video is widespread across UK policing and there is good evidence of the positive benefits to both public interest and effective policing. The Authority supports its wider roll-out in Scotland as a matter of priority. As with all technologies, the appropriate checks and balances will need to be in place to ensure data protection and privacy concerns are considered fully and managed carefully. This research reports some of the key assurances and training protocols that the Authority would expect to be provided in the rollout of BWV.”</p>
<p>Professor Webster said it was extremely important that organisations, such as the police, continue to consult with the public and with academics around the introduction of new technologies. He said: “Practitioners such as the police are usually not in a position to accumulate all the knowledge they need, so it’s really important they work with academics who can do so, so that they introduce technologies in an accountable way that serves the interests of the public.”&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://dspace.stir.ac.uk/handle/1893/34460#.Yv4jZC7MI2w">Read the full report here</a></strong></p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Success for Stirling Swimmer at Euro Champs</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/success-for-stirling-swimmer-at-euro-champs/</link>
				<pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 11:08:18 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/success-for-stirling-swimmer-at-euro-champs/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong><span data-contrast="auto">University of Stirling sport scholar Lucy Hope has enjoyed a great run of form at this year’s European Aquatic Championships in Rome.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></strong></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">On the second night of the event, Hope secured her first medal. Taking a silver in the 200m Freestyle Relay alongside teammates Freya Colbert, Medi Harris and Freya Anderson.&nbsp;</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">Narrowly missing out on gold to the Netherlands by just under seven tenths of a second, Hope remained optimistic.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">"I think we were hoping for the gold, but to come away with silver after the morning swim, we can't really be upset. We swam four good legs and we're all really happy with the silver."</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">The next evening would hold more success for the Stirling swimmer, this time in the 100m Freestyle Relay. Teaming up again with Harris and Anderson, but this time joined by Anna Hopkin, the relay team battled through a hotly contested final to take Britain’s first gold of the event.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">Happy to secure the gold for the second consecutive year, Lucy said: "I was happy to go faster than in my individual, and to get the gold with the girls, it's what we came here to do, as defending champions there's a bit of pressure - but I think we all knew that if we put four good legs together, we could get the gold. We all had four good swims, so I'm really happy with tonight".</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">The swimming scholar also added to her silverware count in the heats, picking up another gold and silver medal respectively in the 200m Mixed Freestyle Relay and 100m Mixed Freestyle Relay.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">Lucy Hope is part of the University’s </span><a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/student-life/sport-at-stirling/performance-sport/swimming/"><span data-contrast="none"><span data-ccp-charstyle="Hyperlink">high performance swimming p</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="Hyperlink">r</span><span data-ccp-charstyle="Hyperlink">ogramme</span></span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> which supports students in combining their studies with training and competing at the highest level of sport.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>]]></description>
				<category>sports-centre</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Record medal haul for Stirling athletes at Commonwealth Games
</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/record-medal-haul-for-stirling-athletes-at-commonwealth-games/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 09:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/record-medal-haul-for-stirling-athletes-at-commonwealth-games/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>University of Stirling&nbsp;swimmers have returned from the 2022 Commonwealth Games with a record 16 medals.</strong></p>
<p>Stirling swimming sensation Duncan Scott became Scotland's most decorated Commonwealth athlete of all time as he won six medals in Birmingham - two gold and four bronze - to take his total across three Games to 13.<span data-ccp-props="{&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p>Also in the pool, Ross Murdoch won three bronze medals and Stephen Milne two, while there were also medals for Cameron Kurle (silver), Craig McNally, Mark Szaranek, Toni Shaw, and Martyn Walton (all bronze).</p>
<p>In addition to the 16, two further medals were won by recent graduates of&nbsp;the&nbsp;University's sports scholarship programme. Judoka Rachel Tytler, who&nbsp;left the University&nbsp;last year, and cyclist Finn Crockett, who graduated this summer, both won bronze in their events.</p>
<p>The University of Stirling - Scotland's University for Sporting Excellence since 2008 -&nbsp;had a record number of athletes selected for this year's Games. Twenty&nbsp;current athletes travelled to Birmingham, as well as six recent graduates - and the medal haul far surpasses the 11&nbsp;won at the Gold Coast Games in 2018.</p>
<p>University of Stirling Executive Director of Sport, Cathy Gallagher, said: “The results and performances over the Games have been fantastic and it’s great to see such camaraderie amongst the athletes. The support being shown across the different teams is what the Commonwealth Games are all about and seeing so many world-class athletes compete in such a positive environment is a brilliant advert for sport.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“With so many University athletes at the Games, there is a real buzz around campus and the city of Stirling and everyone is taking a lot of pride in their achievements.”</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr><th scope="col"><strong>Athlete</strong></th><th scope="col">Country</th><th scope="col">Medals</th></tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Duncan Scott</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>200m Individual Medley (gold); 200m Freestyle (gold); 400m Individual Medley (bronze); 100m Freestyle (bronze); 4x200m Freestyle Relay (bronze); 4x100m Medley Relay (bronze)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ross Murdoch</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>200m Breaststroke (bronze); 50m Breaststroke (bronze); 4x100m Medley Relay (bronze)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stephen Milne</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>4x200m Freestyle Relay&nbsp;(bronze);&nbsp;4x100m Medley Relay (bronze)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cameron Kurle</td>
<td>England</td>
<td>4x100m&nbsp;Freestyle Relay (silver)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Craig McNally</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>4x100m Medley Relay (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mark Szaranek</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>4x200m Freestyle Relay (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Toni Shaw</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>100m Freestyle Para Sport S9 (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Martyn Walton</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>4x100m Medley Relay (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rachel Tytler (recent graduate)</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>Judo Under 78kg (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Finn Crockett (recent graduate)</td>
<td>Scotland</td>
<td>Cycling Road Race (bronze)&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2>Duncan Scott</h2>
<p>Scott won&nbsp;gold - setting a new Games Record of 1:56.88 in the process - in the 200m Individual Medley, before&nbsp;securing another bronze in the 100m Medley Relay with fellow Stirling swimmers McNally and Murdoch, alongside&nbsp;Team Scotland teammate Evan Jones. The win also marked a Scottish Record too, coming home&nbsp;in 3:35.11 and narrowly beating the record previously set at the Gold Coast. Stirling athletes Walton and Milne were also awarded bronze medals having raced in the heat.</p>
<p>Scott&nbsp;had already won 100m Freestyle bronze before producing a phenomenal anchor leg to secure bronze in the 4x200m Freestyle Relay&nbsp;earlier at the Games alongside Stirling&nbsp;duo Milne and Szaranek, and Scotland teammate Jones.</p>
<p>He also claimed gold in the 200m Freestyle after pipping GB teammate, Tom Dean, in a reverse of last year’s Olympic final, before going again to win bronze in the 400m Individual Medley later in the same session.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/Duncan-Scott-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Duncan Scott on podium with gold medal" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption"><span data-contrast="none">Record-breaking Duncan Scott (Photo: Team Scotland)</span></p>
<p>Following a disrupted lead-up to the Games, Scott was happy to be back on the podium. He said: “I wouldn’t have done the double if I wasn’t confident, I know my own ability that is why I trusted myself, the process and more importantly I trusted the coach.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"I have so much trust in what Steve says and what we have done for the last few years. He has got a lot of faith in my ability, and I just had to go out there and do it.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"I like to race quite a lot and this year didn’t present that opportunity. I was gutted to miss the Worlds. I love being part of those team relays as well, I am really happy to be here and do what I can.”</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/Toni-SHaw-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Toni Shaw with flag over shoulders wearing bronze medal" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p><span class="c-image-caption">Toni Shaw takes bronze. (Photo: Team Scotland)</span></p>
<h2>Shaw and Murdoch</h2>
<p>Shaw and Murdoch secured&nbsp;Stirling's&nbsp;first medals of the Games with a bronze each in the S9 100m Freestyle and 200m Breaststroke. Kurle also bagged himself a&nbsp;silver in the 4x100m Freestyle Relay with Team England, having swum in the heats.</p>
<p>Competing at her second Games, Business Studies student Shaw&nbsp;reacted to her win: “I am absolutely buzzing and I do not have any words; I was most excited to get one of the toy bulls. I knew it was going to be really close with so many other girls with a similar time, so I am glad to be on the right side of the finish line this time.</p>
<p>"My family haven’t seen me race in person for such a long time, tonight was really special.</p>
<p>"It was such a competitive race and so close, but I am happy with how it turned out, and seeing Katie (Shanahan) get a medal earlier on, really spurred us on to do well."</p>
<p>The excitement didn't stop there as Murdoch went on to win bronze in the 50m Breaststroke in another gutsy performance.</p>
<p>Following a break from the sport in December, Murdoch’s success has been a highlight of the Games. Speaking after that win, Murdoch acknowledged the support he’d received on his return: “I just want to say thanks very much to the guys at University of Stirling, first and foremost, for allowing me the time to get the ‘heid’ back, so I can keep it!</p>
<p>"So thanks very much to those guys for letting me get it, and find it again, and find the love for my sport, and welcome me back to the ‘trenches’ with open arms.&nbsp;To Scottish Swimming for letting me come back as well and believing in me. And to the Institute of Sport for the absolutely unbelievable support they have given me since 2011.&nbsp;</p>
<p>"Standing here at a third Commonwealth Games, it honestly doesn’t get better.”</p>
<p><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0}"><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/Text-pic-Rachel_TYTLER_Day6_Judo_Medal-(3).jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Rachel Tytler with her bronze medal" loading="lazy" />
 </span></p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Judoka Rachel Tytler&nbsp;on the podium. (Photo: Team Scotland)</p>
<p>Outside of swimming, Stirling graduate and judoka Tytler earned her first Games medal, securing a bronze by ippon within the first 30 seconds of her bout against Canada's Coralie Godbout. And in cycling,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/2022/july-2022-news/team-scotland-cyclist-graduates-ahead-of-commonwealth-games-bow/">fellow graduate Crockett</a> produced a magnificent sprint finish in the road race event to win bronze and his&nbsp;first major medal.</p>]]></description>
				<category>sports-centre</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Monocultures or mixed species? Surprising research shows how forests cope with drought</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/monocultures-or-mixed-species-surprising-new-research-shows-how-different-forests-cope-with-drought/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 15:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/monocultures-or-mixed-species-surprising-new-research-shows-how-different-forests-cope-with-drought/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Monocultures of some of the UK’s most economically important conifers may be more resilient to spring drought than mixed species forests, new research has shown.</strong></p>
<p>Although mixed-species forests can be more productive and provide a wider range of social, environmental and economic benefits than those containing a single species, they may not be as resilient to drought, the University of Stirling researchers found.</p>
<p>Using a long-term experimental forest in Ardross, near Inverness in Scotland, they measured the impact of a spring drought in 2012 on monocultures of two species - Sitka spruce and Scots pine - compared to mixtures of the same two species growing together in different proportions.</p>
<p>Scots pine and Sitka spruce are two of the most economically important timber species in the UK, collectively making up 68% of all the UK’s coniferous forest area, with Sitka spruce alone comprising 51%.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/august/Tom-Ovendon_University-of-Stirling-text-pic.jpg" width="1240" height="620" alt="Tom Ovenden" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Tom Ovenden</p>
<p>PhD researcher Tom Ovenden, of the Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences, who led the study, said: “As expected, we found evidence that Scots pine was more resistant to drought than Sitka spruce. However, to our surprise, monocultures of both species appeared to be more resilient to spring drought than any of the mixtures of the two species that we considered.</p>
<h2>Increasing resilience</h2>
<p>“As we rapidly try to adapt our forests to deal with the challenges of a changing climate, it’s important that decisions on how best to achieve this are based on robust scientific evidence. This work is important because it demonstrates that simply adding more tree species to a forest does not automatically increase its resilience. Instead, the existence of any beneficial effects of species mixture likely depends on which species are mixed, their characteristics and how they interact.</p>
<p>“Understanding how to effectively increase forest resilience is important, as the ability of forests to sequester carbon, provide habitat for a range of species and to continue to deliver a range of ecosystems services is dependent on them being robust to climate change.”</p>
<h2>Measuring growth in tree rings</h2>
<p>Mr Ovenden and his team collected tree cores – samples extracted from the trunks – to examine the tree rings that document the annual variation in tree growth. He said: “As tree growth is partly driven by how favourable a given year’s climate is, by collecting and measuring tree rings, we can quantify how much of an impact an extreme event such as this 2012 drought had on tree growth.</p>
<p>“Unexpectedly, we also found no evidence that competition from surrounding trees had a role in regulating either tree resistance - their ability to withstand the impact of drought - or their resilience - their ability to get back to normal after to drought. This may be because the forest was still relatively young, at 24 years, when the drought occurred.”</p>
<h2>More&nbsp;research needed</h2>
<p>Professor Alistair Jump, Dean of Stirling’s Faculty of Natural Sciences and a co-author of the study, highlighted the need for more research to understand how resilient native and non-native trees are under a range of UK soils and climate conditions.</p>
<p>Professor Jump said: “We currently know very little about how resilient tree species growing in the UK are to drought and other extreme events, and this lack of evidence makes it difficult for forest managers to effectively adapt to climate change.</p>
<p>“As a result, there is an urgent need for us to understand the historic impact of drought and other extreme weather events, as well as predict the impact of future events under a range of possible climate change scenarios for different species and forest types.”</p>
<p>Mr Ovenden’s research is funded by the University of Stirling, Forest Research, and the Scottish Forestry Trust. The paper <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S037811272200442X">‘Intimate mixtures of Scots pine and Sitka spruce do not increase resilience to spring drought’</a> is published in the journal Forest Ecology and Management.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Study reveals negative experience of family caregivers during the pandemic</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/study-reveals-negative-experience-of-family-caregivers-during-the-pandemic/</link>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 15:08:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/august-2022-news/study-reveals-negative-experience-of-family-caregivers-during-the-pandemic/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Family caregivers in the UK were marginalised during the pandemic, and vulnerable older people were let down by the health system, a new study has found.</strong></p>
<p>Caregivers felt “powerless, voiceless and choiceless” during the first six months of the pandemic, as chaos reigned in some parts of the health system, elderly relatives were prematurely discharged and health records sometimes changed without due process, the University of Stirling Management School research found.</p>
<p>Dr Carolyn Wilson-Nash analysed 2607 posts on forums for UK-based family caregivers between March 15 and September 15, 2020. She said: “When the pandemic hit, the NHS responded by postponing non-emergency procedures, closing non-emergency services and redeploying specialists, which released necessary hospital beds. Unfortunately, these actions had negative consequences for older people and their carers.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>Student films get debut on BBC iPlayer</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/student-films-get-debut-on-bbc-iplayer/</link>
				<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 10:07:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/student-films-get-debut-on-bbc-iplayer/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Two short films created by University of Stirling students as part of a unique partnership with BBC Scotland are being showcased by the broadcaster online.</strong></p>
<p>Developed in collaboration with BBC Scotland’s flagship journalism strand ‘Disclosure’, the documentaries ‘<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/p0cl69k5/disclosure-shorts-do-i-have-adhd">Do I Have ADHD?</a>’ and <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/p0cl6d14/disclosure-shorts-is-my-flat-safe">‘Is My Flat Safe?’</a> were presented, filmed and edited by graduating&nbsp;<a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/subjects/film-and-media-studies/">Film and Media</a> and <a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/subjects/journalism-and-publishing/">Journalism </a>students. They have now been released on BBC iPlayer.</p>
<p>&nbsp;The films were created following a series of masterclasses led by senior BBC journalists, and students were invited to pitch ideas for a documentary. Two were then commissioned, with&nbsp;teams of five students receiving mentoring and support from BBC staff including Disclosure editor, Shelley Jofre and Journalist Mark Daly – both of whom are Stirling graduates.</p>
<p>Kirsty Craib, Alice Williams, Danielle Hilton, Andrew Lockhart and Caitlin Campbell made ‘Do I Have ADHD?<strong><em>’ </em></strong>in which reporter Kirsty explores the issues around diagnosis of the condition in girls and young women, while also pursuing her own journey to discover if she has the condition. Kim Drummond, Stan Stawowiak, Caroline Ring, Shoshannah Hull and Cameron Hutchinson made ‘Is My Flat Safe?’, investigating the living conditions experienced by some Edinburgh social housing residents struggling with damp and mould.</p>]]></description>
				<category></category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>New exhibition celebrates Scotland&#8217;s Commonwealth Games heroes</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/new-exhibition-celebrates-scotlands-commonwealth-games-heroes-/</link>
				<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 13:07:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/new-exhibition-celebrates-scotlands-commonwealth-games-heroes-/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p><strong>A new exhibition curated by University of Stirling experts to celebrate Scotland’s historic sporting heroes is set to open in Birmingham as part of the 2022 Commonwealth Games.</strong></p>
<p>‘Walking in the Footsteps of Heroes’ is based on the Commonwealth Games Scotland Archive held in the University’s collections and celebrates equality, diversity and inclusion among Team Scotland’s former medal winners.</p>
<p>Opening on Wednesday 27 July at Scotland House – the home-from-home for Team Scotland at the Birmingham event – the exhibition includes a timeline of Team Scotland heroes from every Games since 1930 and displays key materials including commemorative medals, historic memorabilia and Team Scotland athletic wear.</p>
<p>It is the third year Professor Richard Haynes and University Archivist Karl Magee have developed a sporting display for Scotland House, with the pair having previously travelled to the Gold Coast and Glasgow Games to present previous exhibitions.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/july/Scotland-Ladies-Swimming-Team-British-Empire-Games-1930-1240x730.jpg" width="1240" height="730" alt="Scotland Ladies Swimming Team British Empire Games 1930" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p class="c-image-caption">Scotland Ladies Swimming Team, British Empire Games 1930&nbsp;</p>
<p>Professor Haynes said: “Once again, it is an honour to work with Team Scotland to celebrate their heritage and to share significant stories emerging from their collection.</p>
<p>“Walking in the Footsteps of Heroes includes household names of Scottish sport, but it also spotlights athletes who have been forgotten over time, such as Rosemary Harvey who won four medals for Scotland in a number of wheelchair throwing events and archery in Perth 1962.</p>
<p>“We were asked to showcase the diversity of heroes who have represented Scotland at the Games, and I hope we have managed to achieve this in our selection of personal stories. The exhibition should certainly be a talking point to visitors to Scotland House in Birmingham”</p>
<p>The exhibition profiles Scotland’s female athletes, those from a diverse ethnic or national background who chose to represent Scotland, and pioneers of Scottish para-sports. It also celebrates those athletes with cross-generational family representation for Team Scotland, such as the Heatly’s, McColgan’s, McIntosh’s and Flockhart’s.</p>
<p><strong>Featured athletes</strong></p>
<p><strong>Cissie Stewart, Hamilton 1930</strong></p>
<p>The women’s swimming team were the first female participants for Team Scotland – this included double-medallist Cissie Stewart from Dundee who, during the trip to Canada in 1930, eloped with her fiancée and journalist Bill Hunt<strong>.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Joanne Flockhart, Edmonton 1978</strong></p>
<p>Badminton player Flockhart was the only female medallist for Scotland of these Games, taking silver in the Badminton Mixed Doubles alongside Billy Gilliland. Flockhart’s son, Bruce, also represented Scotland at Badminton, and like his mum played in three consecutive Games, from 1994 to 2002.</p>
<p><strong>Angela Bridgeman Baxter, Brisbane 1982</strong></p>
<p>Angela was a sprinter who was born in London and brought to Glasgow as a four-month-old baby by her Trinidad-born parents. In September 1981, she became one of the first recipients of a sports scholarship at the University of Stirling. Angela went on to represent Scotland in the 1982 Commonwealth Games at Brisbane, winning a bronze medal in the 4 x 400m event.&nbsp; She competed for Scotland in two Commonwealth Games and ranked in the top 10 in every event she competed in between 1980 and 1993.</p>
<p><strong>Liz McColgan Nuttal MBE, Edinburgh 1986</strong></p>
<p>Competing under her maiden name Liz Lynch, Nuttall won Scotland’s only gold medal in athletics in the 10,000m. Nuttall’s refrain, “Don’t be afraid to dream big!”, clearly had a significant impact on her daughter Eilish McColgan who has represented Scotland at the Games since 2014, and in 2021 broke Paula Radcliffe’s long-standing UK record for the women’s 5000m.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/july/1986-Book-Liz-Lynch-700x600.jpg" width="700" height="600" alt="Liz Lynch on the track in 1986 Commonwealth Games in Edinburgh" loading="lazy" />
</p>
<p><strong>Loretta Cusack Doyle, Auckland 1990</strong></p>
<p>Judo appeared for the first time in 1990 and Loretta Cusack-Doyle Cusack won the gold medal in the lightweight (56kg) event – Scotland’s first Commonwealth medal in the sport.</p>
<p><strong>Steve Frew, Manchester 2002</strong></p>
<p>Competing in his fourth Commonwealth Games in Manchester in July 2002, Frew made history for Team Scotland when he won the men's rings event. It was Scotland's first-ever gymnastics Commonwealth Games gold medal.</p>
<p><img src="/media/stirling/news/news-centre/2022/july/SteveFrew700x600.jpg" width="600" height="700" alt="Steve Frew receives his Commonwealth gold medal" loading="lazy" />
 </p>
<p><strong>Neil Fachie, Glasgow 2014</strong></p>
<p>Fachie won gold in both Time Trial and Sprint at Glasgow 2014 with pilot Craig MacLean. He made it a ‘double double’, also winning both events at Gold Coast 2018 with pilot Matt Rotherham, setting World and Games records in Sprint qualifying and a Games record in the Time Trial.</p>
<p><strong>Eilidh Doyle, Gold Coast 2018</strong></p>
<p>Team Scotland’s first ever female Flag Bearer at an Opening Ceremony was Eilidh Doyle who took silver at Gold Coast 2018, her third successive Commonwealth Games silver over 400m Hurdles. Alongside a glittering array of Olympic, World and European medals, it cemented Eilidh’s place as Scotland’s most decorated track &amp; field athlete of all-time.</p>
<p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
						<item>
				<title>How the humble sea cucumber could transform fish farming</title>
				<link>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/how-the-humble-sea-cucumber-could-transform-fish-farming/</link>
				<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 15:07:00 BST</pubDate>
				<guid>https://www.stir.ac.uk/news/news-archive/../2022/july-2022-news/how-the-humble-sea-cucumber-could-transform-fish-farming/</guid>
				<description><![CDATA[<p>Help to solve one of the world’s most pressing dilemmas - how to feed our growing population whilst protecting the planet – may be at hand from a surprising ally – the sea cucumber.</p>
<p>New research led by the University of Stirling’s Institute of Aquaculture shows how sea cucumbers – a delicacy in Asia – can flourish by feeding and growing on organic waste released from commercial fish farms in the Mediterranean.</p>
<p>The discovery means adding sea cucumbers can reduce the environmental impacts of marine fish farming whilst providing a high value extra product. Mediterranean sea cucumbers can fetch between €30/kg dried and €120/kg as processed product, where farmed sea bream are currently worth just six euros per kilo.</p>]]></description>
				<category>research</category>
			</item>
			
	</channel>
</rss>